A Guide to the Papers of Charles G. Halpine 1863-1868
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Charles G. Halpine 1863-1868
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7719
9 items
Forms part of the Clifton Waller Barrett Library
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Clifton Waller Barrett
Biographical/Historical Information
Irish born American author; Brigadier General in the Union army; best known for his humorous description of Civil War events in "The Life and Adventures...of Private Miles O'Reilly."
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains manuscripts of two poems by Halpine, six letters from him and a drawing.
Contents List
- Manuscripts
  - Poem The Chemisetten.d., AMsS 2 p.
  - Printed poem beginning with her charming looks... on the verso of which is hand written the poem We are coming Father Abraham by James Sloan Gibbons 1863 Mar 25, AMS 2 p.
- Letters
  - Charles G. Halpine to George Washington Cullum 1863 Nov 26, ALS 3 p.
    Reports on "Private Miles," the fictitious army private he created, and on an interview with President Abraham Lincoln; notes that a report on the latter will be in Saturday's Herald. Includes the poem Nora Creina.
  - Charles G. Halpine to Charles Nordhoff 1864 Apr 7, ALS 4 p.
    Asks Nordhoff to review the appended poem titled April 20th '64 and signed "Miles O'Reilly." Also asks Nordhoff to show the poem to William Cullen Bryant for his opinion.
  - Charles G. Halpine to George Washington Cullum 1864 Apr 21, ALS 4 p.
    Reports on information regarding General Ulysses Grant. Offers high praise for General Henry W. Halleck, suggesting he could have been Democratic nominee for President. Refers to his own resignation and new career with a law firm.
  - Charles G. Halpine to Douglas Taylor 1867 Feb 21, ALS (electrostatic copy) 2 p.
    Confirms appointment. Insists on being assessed his share of expenses. Mentions a Mr. Fowler
  - Charles G. Halpine to Salmon P. Chase 1868 Apr 1, ALS 3 p.
    Urges Chase to seek the Democratic nomination for President in 1868 in the moderate conservative wing, to oppose George Pendleton, who had been the Democratic vice-presidential nominee in 1864.
  - Charles G. Halpine to John M. Savage 1868 Jul 22, ALS 2 p.
    Asks employment for a Thomas Molony, a "Fenian Refugee."
- Miscellaneous
  - Drawing n.d.
    Drawing from a photograph showing Halpine in the uniform of his literary character "Private Miles O'Reilly."